Hello, my name is Jeimmy Walteros and it is a pleasure to share with you the knowledge
and experiences on the topics of climate change and climate variability.
Remember that this diploma in citizen participation for the fight against climate change
is part of the intelligent personal learning environments project
co-financed by the European Union.
Climate change is not a problem of the future, it is here and it affects us all.
This event, recorded over a wide time scale, becomes the greatest threat affecting our planet and our existence.
Although it can be considered a natural event, anthropogenic activities have accelerated it in recent centuries.
As a result of combustion and industrial activities, greenhouse gases such as carbon dioxide are being emitted,
nitrogen and sulfur oxides, as well as a series of primary and secondary pollutants that alter our system.
Some natural causes of climate change are solar activity, which influences the greenhouse effect.
However, this contributes to global warming.
Historically, atypical changes have been recorded, characterized by very cold or very warm seasons.
However, today, climate change is significantly and steadily transforming the global climate, intensifying phenomena of climate variability
that are increasingly frequent and extreme.
Another relevant natural factor is volcanic activity, which modifies the chemical composition of the atmosphere due to volcanic eruptions that release large amounts of
It will then be necessary to reduce, recycle, reuse, recover, and reinvent ourselves to avoid the negative impacts left by plastics and other non-biodegradable products.
particles, as well as gases of
Climate change is advancing and is becoming increasingly important in our countries.
nitrogen and sulfur oxides that contribute to greenhouse gases.
this the release of carbon stored in vegetation and soils.
Since the Industrial Revolution, climate change has accelerated.
which play a fundamental role in the processes of regulation and transformation of
The main culprits are the consumption of fossil fuels and industrial development
located in some world powers and mainly in urban regions.
Also intensive activities such as agriculture, livestock, even mining,
as well as the deforestation of large tracts of land can be
evident in rural areas.
As long as humanity exists, solid waste will be generated.
It will then be necessary to reduce, recycle, reuse, recover, and reinvent ourselves to avoid
the negative impacts left by plastics and other non-biodegradable products.
Climate change is advancing and is becoming increasingly important in our countries.
In Colombia and Peru, the deforestation of their tropical forests is increasing and with
this the release of carbon stored in vegetation and soils.
This event is leading to the loss of habitat for a diversity of living forms,
which play a fundamental role in the processes of regulation and transformation of
nutrients.
The Amazon, considered the lung of the world, is a territory shared by these nations.
and is increasingly threatened by intensive activities such as agriculture, livestock, and mining, considerably increasing the concentrations of carbon dioxide,
methane, and nitrous oxide.
Central American countries such as Mexico and Nicaragua are highly vulnerable to climate change.
Mexico, a megadiverse country, faces various challenges.
It has the tensions of areas of deforested forests, as well as marine ecosystems deteriorated by the increase in temperature and the acidification of its water mass, and
the catastrophic impacts due to increasingly intense and frequent storms and hurricanes.
Heat waves and cold periods in some regions have accelerated the desertification of large areas of land.
As a consequence, local communities are losing their agrobiodiversity.
Water is increasingly scarce and soils are losing nutrients.
The same happens in Nicaragua, where the increase in ambient temperature leaves intense droughts
and directly threatens the agricultural production of corn, coffee, and cocoa, the main products of this nation.
European countries such as Portugal, Spain, and Romania are working on the implementation of projects for the use of renewable energies, especially wind and solar.
However, the energy transition towards a fully sustainable model is progressing slowly.
Industrial growth entails a high energy demand and this means that greenhouse gas levels are increasingly higher.
putting at risk the achievement of reduction, mitigation, and adaptation goals.
It is important to highlight that Spain has implemented the Climate Change and Energy Transition Law, which seeks climate neutrality by 2050.
As part of these policies, sustainable alternatives such as public transport, the use of bicycles, and car sharing are being promoted.
Despite the path of positive actions, this nation remains vulnerable to extreme weather events, such as severe floods, prolonged droughts, heavy snowfalls
and episodes of intense cold.
Romania also faces serious problems due to the desertification of its soils, which are increasingly sandy, with scarce availability of nutrients and water, putting at risk the
agricultural production
and with this the food security of its country.
We are experiencing the effects of climate change now.
For example, the rise in surface temperatures of the planet.
In the last decade, from 2011 to 2020, greater warming has been recorded to date.
Since then, each decade has been warmer than the previous one.
Climate change is also modifying water availability.
by making it much scarcer in some regions.
With droughts, the vulnerability of ecosystems and the risk of availability for communities increases.
Another is storms, which have become more intense, frequent, and devastating in some regions.
As the temperature rises, more humidity is generated in the atmosphere, which causes extreme precipitation.
Ocean warming also affects the frequency and magnitude of storms, cyclones, and hurricanes, even typhoons, which are causing serious disasters and a
greater impact on the economy and our communities.
Understanding the climate system involves understanding the complex and interconnected dynamics that exist between the atmosphere, the oceans, and the earth's surface.
Natural phenomena such as climate variability are increasingly intense and difficult to face.
These alterations cause drastic climate fluctuations in relatively short periods such as years, seasons, or even decades.
They have always existed, but now they are much more dangerous.
For example, the ENSO phenomenon known in the Pacific as the Southern Oscillation
is influenced by the temperatures of ocean currents and atmospheric pressure.
During the El Niño phenomenon, warm currents reduce evaporation and cloud formation, generating drier periods with less precipitation.
In contrast, La Niña is characterized by ocean cooling that increases humidity and causes heavy rains.
The challenge is to transform management and participation in our territories and adapt to change.
We must seek nature-based solutions that reduce social, economic, and natural impacts.
This implies working in favor of the conservation and restoration of our ecosystems, improving infrastructures, and even addressing problems with local communities.
The challenge is to reduce poverty.
to avoid forced migrations, ensure food, live in spaces more adapted to realities, and reduce social inequality.
We all depend on nature to live.
That is why we must take action towards co-management so that our nations can fulfill the commitments made.
In this way, we will ensure that our economies and our model are increasingly
more resilient and ready for transformation and change processes.
Our commitment is now.
We must act to mitigate and adapt to climate change with actions that lead to diversifying food production, protecting natural resources, ensuring
water so that it is sufficient and of good quality, preserving biodiversity, investing in sustainable infrastructures and clean and efficient energies.
It will be necessary to think of an economy
that allows our organizations and communities to be increasingly resilient.
We must increase capacity and resources at the local level, convene and participate more, make information and generated knowledge available, permeate cultures, their
knowledge, expand knowledge dialogue tables and learning processes.
Only with knowledge and commitment will it be possible to take care of our society.
and nature.
You are doing very well.
Thank you for your attention and for your learning.
In this way, you have completed this first part.
Thank you very much.